<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Spiritual marriage: or, The vnion betweene Christ and his Church As it was delivered in a sermon at Westminster, the first of Ianuarie. Anno Dom. 1626. By Iames Baillie, Master of Arts.</title>
            <author>Baillie, James, Master of Arts.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1627</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 103 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01889</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1203</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120307</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855506</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855506</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21001</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01889)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21001)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 620:6, 2340:8i)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Spiritual marriage: or, The vnion betweene Christ and his Church As it was delivered in a sermon at Westminster, the first of Ianuarie. Anno Dom. 1626. By Iames Baillie, Master of Arts.</title>
                  <author>Baillie, James, Master of Arts.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by B. A[lsop] and T. Favvcet, for Robert Allot, and are to be sold at his shop, at the blacke Beare in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1627.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Printer's device (McK. 339) on t.p.; headpieces, initials.</note>
                  <note>The item at reel 2340:8i is ninth in a group of ten items bound and filmed together.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: copy at reel 2340:8i lacks t.p.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in: Cambridge University Library (reel 620:6) and Boston Public Library (reel 2340:8i).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Hosea II, 19 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21001:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21001:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SPIRITVAL MARRIAGE: <hi>OR,</hi> THE VNION <hi>betweene</hi> CHRIST <hi>and his</hi> CHVRCH.</p>
            <p>As it was delivered in a Sermon at WESTMINSTER, the firſt of Ianuarie. ANNO DOM. 1626.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> IAMES BAILLIE, <hi>Maſter of Arts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON. Printed by B.A. and T. FAVVCET, for ROBERT ALLOT, and are to be ſold at his Shop, at the blacke <hi>Beare</hi> in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1627.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:21001:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21001:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE,
<list>
                     <item>IAMES, <hi>Marquis of</hi> HAMMILTON.</item>
                     <item>WILLIAM, <hi>Earle of</hi> MORTON.</item>
                     <item>WILLIAM, <hi>Earle of</hi> LAVTHIAN.</item>
                     <item>THOMAS, <hi>Earle of</hi> KELLIE.</item>
                     <item>IAMES, <hi>Earle of</hi> CARLILL.</item>
                     <item>RICHARD, <hi>Earle of</hi> DESMONT.</item>
                     <item>IOHN, <hi>Earle of</hi> ANNANDAILL.</item>
                     <item>WILLIAM, <hi>Vice count of</hi> AIRE.</item>
                     <item>GEORGE, <hi>Lord</hi> BRVCE.</item>
                  </list> And to the Right Worſhipfull,
<list>
                     <item>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. IAMES FVLLERTON, <hi>Groome of his Maieſt. Stoole.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. ROBERT CAR, <hi>Gentleman of his Maieſt. Bed-cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and Keeper of the Privie-purſe.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. IAMES MAXVVELL,</item>
                     <item>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. KIRKE,</item>
                     <item>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. WILLIAM MVRRAY,</item>
                     <item>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. IAMES LEVINGSTON,</item>
                  </list> 
                  <hi>and</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. PIT CARNE, <hi>Groomes of his Maieſties Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chamber.</hi> And to all other Hon: and Wor: Scotſmen re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining at the Court of <hi>England,</hi> that profeſſe the true Ancient, Catholike, and Apoſtolike faith, all bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Happineſſe in this life, and Eternall bliſſe in the life to come.
<pb facs="tcp:21001:3"/> 
                  <hi>Right</hi> HONOVRABLE, <hi>and</hi> WORSHIPFVLL.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ome perhaps may thinke that I haue done an abſurd thing in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixing ſo many illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Peeres, prudent Nobles, and Gentlemen of his Maieſties Bed-chamber, of high and great deſert, to ſo little and ſo ſlender a worke: But from the learned I hope for a leſſe critick cenſure, and from the wiſe for a more judicious ſentence: firſt, becauſe I know that this weake treatiſe hath need not only of one ſtrong pillar, but of many to vphold it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ruine, which both by Papiſts; and falſe Brethren, will maliciouſly bee threatened againſt it: and againſt their ſubterranian plots, by which at e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very corner they will intend to vndermine it. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe, I will never deny but any one of your Hon: or Wor: is a prop more then ſufficient enough to ſuſtaine a more decaying edifice, if any ſuch can be apprehended: and a booke of greater worth ſhould haue but too much honour to haue any one of your names in its frontiſpiece. Secondly, becauſe I would encourage you, and rouze vp your ſpirits to a liuelie confidence, that by adoption you are the ſonnes of Gods right hand, members of his body, fleſh of his fleſh, and bone of his bone, a part of that choſen ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration,
<pb facs="tcp:21001:3"/> 
               <hi>The Church of the elect and ſpouſe of Chriſt,</hi> by marriage vnited vnto him, and freed from that An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian ſlaverie and Babilonian bondage, with the wine of whoſe fornication a great part of the world theſe many ages paſt haue beene made drunke, and therefore God hath made you ſtrong, ſtrong for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in this time of triall when the ſonnes of Anti-chriſt breathes nothing but blood againſt the Church of Chriſt; and againſt her in many places of <hi>Germany</hi> haue preuailed, caſten out Chriſt, and in his place ſet vp that abominable Idoll, <hi>their Maſſe,</hi> and now threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth our Church, the Church within this Iſland with the like, to extinguiſh the lampe of the glorious Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, which God hath lighted amongſt vs, to remoue our candleſtick, and in lieu thereof to light falſe lights, to ſet vp ruſty &amp; darke candleſticks, <hi>Their ſeruice in an vnknowne tongue, their Idols in ſtead of inſtructions, and their Apoſtles bones, and clothes in place of the writings of Chriſts Apoſtles.</hi> But God hath made you ſtrong for himſelfe, to fight in his warre, to hold the wild Boares out of his vineyard, and in his cauſe neither to ſpare your bodies nor goods; even in his cauſe, which your Fathers as his inſtruments did re-eſtabliſh in the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchie of <hi>Scotland,</hi> expelling the children of <hi>Dagon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Theſ 2.</note> which had come in <hi>by the effectuall working of Sathan, with all power, and ſignes, and lying wonders, and in all deceiueableneſſe of vnrighteouſneſſe:</hi> and you honoring the Lord after this manner, he will multiply honours vpon you, keepe you as a ſignet vpon his hand,<note place="margin">Ezech 34.</note> and vpon you, and euery one of you, there ſhall be raine of bleſſings, the eye of the Lord ſhall watch ouer you for good, his mighty hand and out ſtretched arme ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:21001:4"/> bee ready to protect you in euery danger, and to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point moſt glorious victories for you: for <hi>Babylon</hi> is now toward the falling, her ſins are come vp to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and God hath remembred her iniquities, ſhee muſt drinke in that cup, that ſhe hath filled to others, and as ſhe hath ſhed our blood, ſo now muſt ſhe be repayed and drinke a double draught.</p>
            <p>Thirdly I haue preſumed to dedicate this Treatiſe vnto your Hon: and Wor: not onely for the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of the ſubiect, <hi>The vnion betweene Chriſt and his Church:</hi> of which you are a part: But likewiſe becauſe I am a Scotſman that haue the honour to belong to euery one of you, either by blood or affinitie, and to many of you by both (whereof I hope you ſhall neuer be aſhamed) and therefore I thought it not amiſſe to let this Sermon go vnder the ſhadow of your Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable protections, that now remaine at the Court of <hi>England,</hi> as an argument of my loue toward my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and as a pledge of my ſeruice toward you all in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, &amp; euery one of you in particular. In the meane ſeaſon continuing my prayers that ſuch a vertuous e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation, may alwaies remaine among you, as is to day; that is, firſt of all, to aduance Gods glory, ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to be loyall to your King, that by innumerable predeceſſors hath ſwayed your Scepter; and laſtly, ſome of you with <hi>Pompie</hi> to ſtudy to preſerue your Dignitie, others with <hi>Craſſus</hi> to augment it, and the third ſort with <hi>Caeſar</hi> to acquire Dignitie, not by vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation, as he did, But in your Soueraignes ſeruice, vnder the banner of CHRIST. Farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours, and Worſhips, moſt humble Seruant <hi>IAMES BAILLIE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:21001:4"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristian Reader, J haue not vſed (as many doe) in this Sermon, the neat Tenour of <hi>ISOCRATES,</hi> the ample Sublimitie of DEMOSTHENES, the Majeſtie of <hi>THVCYCIDES,</hi> the Dignitie of <hi>PLATO,</hi> nor that moſt full and copious ſtile of declamation which <hi>TVLLIE</hi> vſed before the Senate, yea I haue ſhunned them, as by a good Master <hi>SCILLA</hi> and <hi>CARYBDIS</hi> will bee eſchewed; becauſe I know that ſuch garulitie, ſuch fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible inticements of words, and ſuch vaine oſtentation in Preaching, ſauoureth the fleſh, and hath no power, no vertue nor efficacie to wound a proud minde and to caſt it downe, nor to be a balme for the curing and raiſing vp of the ſame againe to a liuely confidence in <hi>CHRIST:</hi> Jt onely tendeth to tickle the auditors eares for the preſent, to enter at the one, and goe forth at the other, but neuer to deſcend into the heart for its circumciſion and molification in time to come. A ſimple ſtile without ſuperfluitie in words, fertile in ſentences, which doth not ſo much ſmell of humaine prudencie, as ſauour the vertue of the holy Spirit, is the onely eloquence that pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trates the ſoules of Chriſtian men, and ſearcheth, to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward marrow of the ſame. It is truth that an Orator once perſwaded <hi>CAESAR</hi> to retreit and reſcinde the ſentence of <hi>LIGARIVS</hi> after that hee was condemned, But when a Miniſter of Gods word, a faithfull Paſtor muſt diſcharge his commiſſion vnto his Flocke, what Rhetorick ſhall make them
<pb facs="tcp:21001:5"/> beleeue that life flowed from the Croſſe of <hi>CHRIST:</hi> that deaths Empire by death was ſubdued, that the eternall word covered with fleſh, beaten with fiſts, nailed to the Croſſe, did beare our ſinnes, die, riſe againe, that we by this benefit ſhall triumph ouer death, and by marriage be vnited vnto him. Here all humaine reaſon, and adminicles of art, though thundered out by a <hi>Pericles,</hi> muſt be abſtained from. Here all pompe in preaching and ſophiſtick oſtentation muſt giue place to the efficatious Paſtor, whoſe ſermon is repleniſhed with ſubſtance, matter, and the riches of the Spirit, which by Saint <hi>PAVL</hi> is called, <hi>2.</hi> Tim. <hi>1.13. Verae doctrinae</hi> hypotypoſis, <hi>The true patterne of wholſome words.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly good reader, albeit, it be barren of humaine elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, yet feare not to read it, for it may be plentifull in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and if thou thinkeſt that J haue ſtayed too much vpon the two firſt ſimilitudes, J thinke ſo with thee myſelfe, <hi>Et ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes confitentem reum,</hi> yee I pray thee to pardon mee, ſeeing it is for thy inſtruction, and diſcouering of much obſtruce and excellent Theologie, by which I hope (and J wiſh it from my heart) that thou ſhalt be bettered, and ſo expecting thy friendly cenſure, J take my leaue. Farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine, in Chriſt to bee commanded,</hi> James Baillie.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:21001:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>SPIRITVALL MARRIAGE; OR, THE VNION BE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene CHRIST and his CHVRCH.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>HOSEA. 2.19.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>J will marrie thee to me for euer, yea I will marrie thee to me.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>LATO Philoſophizing vpon the grace of GOD<note place="margin">Becauſe he was an heathen Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher.</note> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as hee was able, gaue thankes vnto him for three thinges; Firſt, that GOD had created him a Man and not a Beaſt; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, that hee was borne a Grecian and not a Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian. Thirdly, that not only ſo but a Philoſopher alſo. But wee that are inſtructed at a better ſchoole, doe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:21001:6"/> otherwayes deſtribute our thankſgiving, and praiſe him for three things alſo. Firſt, that amongſt all his creatures hee hath made vs men, created in a moſt glorious manner, <hi>Omnino ad imaginem ſuam,</hi> alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether after his owne Image. Secondly that from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all ſorts of men, he hath made vs Chriſtians. Thirdly, that amongſt thoſe, that beare the name of Chriſtians, hee hath made vs onely faithfull ones; elected and adopted vs in his owne Sonne before the foundation of the world,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 1.9.</note> and made vs like a few well ſighted among a throng of blind men, like the por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of IACOB in Aegipt,<note place="margin">Exod. 10.22.</note> onelie enlightened in the middeſt of that darkeneſſe which couered all the Countrie,<note place="margin">Iudg. 6.38.</note> like the fleece of Gideon, onelie watered with the dewe of his grace, whileſt all the reſt of the earth is drie and deſtitute of his fauour.</p>
            <p>When I call to memory the vnſpeakeable loue of GOD, and his fatherly care in the conduct and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of his Church, it is a whole web of won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.<note place="margin">Gen 4.11.</note> How he hath reuenged the blood of ABELL, how he hath ſerued for a pilot and ſteerſman to his Church incloſed within the arke;<note place="margin">Gen. 7.</note> how for the loue of ABRAHAM and ISAACK he hath ſtriken and curbed Kings,<note place="margin">Gen. 12.17.</note> how he hath prepared lodging for his people in Aegipt,<note place="margin">Gen. 48.11.</note> how he hath drawne them from thence with a mighty hand and outſtretched arme hauing caried his people out of captiuitie as vpon Eagles winges,<note place="margin">Exod 14.28.</note> how he hath giuen them his law,<note place="margin">Exod. 20.</note> fed them with bread from heauen,<note place="margin">Exod. 16.15.</note> couered them in the day time, giuen them light in the night, and driuen out Nations be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, how he hath chaſtized them, to keepe them vnder ſubjection in proſperitie, and how his chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:21001:6"/> haue euer beene interlaced with deliuerances, leaſt they ſhould haue beene ouerwhelmed with too great adverſitie: The hiſtorie of the Iudges, of DA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VID and his ſucceſſors, the deliuerance from Babilon, and the re-eſtabliſhment of Ieruſalem. Is not this a whole chaine of GODS mercies, and loue towards his Church linked together already: and yet to make it not onely more weightie, but weight it ſelfe, hee joyneth this linke vnto it, <hi>I will marrie thee to me for euer,</hi> yea, <hi>I will marrie thee vnto me.</hi> And this laſt linke is that which I intend to beſtow vpon you this morning for a New yeeres gift.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Mos vetus eſt Iani dare mutua dona calendis,</l>
               <l>Annus vt auſpicio proſperiore fluat.</l>
            </q>
            <p>It is an ancient cuſtome among friends vpon New yeeres day mutually to giue and to receiue gifts as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate pledges of a hopefull yeere, ſaith a Poet:<note place="margin">Buchan<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> which commonly are of ſiluer, gold, and of precious ſtones.</p>
            <p>But as Saint Peter, <hi>Acts.</hi> 3.6. ſaid of old to the Creeple, that lay at the gate of the Temple called beautifull, <hi>ſiluer and gold haue I none to giue vnto you;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.6.</note> ſo ſay I now vnto you, for I will beſtow no ſuch ware vpon you, thoſe are but droſſe and earth, and of a ruſty and an earthly worth, but ſuch as I haue I will beſtow vpon you, a Spirituall gift, moſt liberally. And if you ſhall but gratefully receiue it, and lay it vp cloſe in the moſt inward cabine of your hearts, I dare bee bold to promiſe that one day it ſhall be helpfull vnto you, miniſter vnto you more joy and comfort, then all the ſiluer, gold, and precious ſtones which are brought from the Orient. And ſo I come to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowing of it, I meane to the handling of my text, <hi>I
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:21001:7"/> will marrie thee to mee for euer,</hi> yea, <hi>I will marrie thee vnto me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This text is a promiſe of comfort, in which you ſhall take notice of theſe foure; Firſt, of the ſubiect, CHRIST; lurking vnder his word, <hi>I;</hi> ſecondly, of the object, the Church, ſheltred vnder this word, <hi>thee.</hi> Thirdly, of the thing promiſed, <hi>Marriage; I will marrie thee.</hi> Fourthly, of the qualities of this marriage, which are two. Firſt, the certaintie imply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the gemination and doubling of the promiſe, <hi>I will marrie thee;</hi> yea, <hi>I will marrie thee.</hi> Laſtly, the perpetuitie of this marriage, <hi>for ever; I will marrie thee vnto mee for ever.</hi> This Propoſition is firſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, <hi>I will marrie thee,</hi> and hereafter explained by a twofold diſtinction; firſt, not to a baſe, not to a diſhonorable match, but to my ſelfe, that am <hi>Gnamith</hi> IEHOVAH,<note place="margin">Eſay. 9.</note> equall to IEHOVAH * the Father of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternitie, who made the earth and ſpred the heavens like a curtaine,<note place="margin">Pſal. 104.</note> the eternall Wiſedome, the eſſentiall Word, the ſecond perſon of the holy Trinitie, GOD euerlaſtingly bleſſed. Secondly, not for a day, a moneth, or a yeere, but perpetually, for euer: and ſo haue you the parts and circumſtances of this Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition: neither minde I to handle them ſeuerally and alone but joyntly and together, becauſe in them joynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is onely contayned that moſt admirable conjuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and moſt ſtrait vnion betweene CHRIST and his Church, which no power in hell nor earth is able to ſunder and infringe: neyther is there any way in nature by which two things can bee made one, but from it the Spirit of GOD borroweth ſimilitudes to expreſſe our conjunction with CHRIST: wee are
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:21001:7"/> one with him, as EVAH was with ADAM, fleſh of his fleſh, and bone of his bone, wee are one with him, as the houſe and the foundation whereupon it is built; But this vnion is moſt liuely ſet forth in theſe three ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militudes. Firſt, as is the ſtrait conjunction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the graft and the ſtock, ſo is the vnion between CHRIST and his Church. Secondly, as is the neere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the garment to the body, ſo is ours with CHRIST. Thirdly, as the ſtraitneſſe of the bond is betweene the wife and the husband, ſuch is the ſtraitneſſe of our vnion with CHRIST.</p>
            <p>But before I explaine the ſimilitudes, it is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to vnderſtand what is ſignified by this word, * <hi>Church,</hi> in my text,<note place="margin">The Church hath diuers ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifications.</note> to the end that you may know to which Church this promiſe is made, ſeeing it is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſly taken, and hath ſundry ſignifications in the old and new Teſtament: for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>the Church,</hi> is a Greeke word and properly ſignifieth an Aſſembly, which belongeth as well to the Heathen, and to Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels, as to Chriſtians and the children of GOD, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified by DAVID, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 26.6.<note place="margin">Pſal. 26.6.</note> 
               <hi>Odini Eccleſiam malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantium, I haue hated the aſſembly;</hi> or, <hi>the Church of the wicked:</hi> and by the Apoſtle, <hi>Act.</hi> 19.<note place="margin">Act. 19.</note> That calleth that multitude, which cryed, <hi>Great is the</hi> DIANA <hi>of the Epheſians, Eccleſiam the aſſembly,</hi> or, <hi>the Church.</hi> But hereafter vſe obtayned that Chriſtians called their aſſembly <hi>Eccleſiam, the Church,</hi> to<note place="margin">Why Chriſtians called there Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies the Church.</note> diſtinguiſh it from the Synagogue of the Iewes, albeit that both <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifieth one thing, an Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, or a Congregation, a meeting or a gathering to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. This word then <hi>Eccleſia the Church,</hi> being vſurped by Chriſtians is taken by them in the new
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:21001:8"/> Teſtament<note place="margin">The Church hath fiue ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications among Chriſtians.</note> fiue manner of wayes. Firſt, for the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors of the Church, the people being excluded, and ſo it is taken S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Math.</hi> 18.17. where our Sauiour commands, That if a debate betweene neighbours cannot bee quietly pacified, to tell the Church; that is the Byſhops, Prelates, and other Paſtors of inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our titles that haue ſuperioritie and juriſdiction in the Church. Now it ſometime belongs to this Church <hi>arguere &amp; increpare,</hi> 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. to improue and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke, ſometimes, <hi>amputare,</hi> to cut off, ſometimes, <hi>lapſos relevare,</hi> to raiſe vp againe ſuch as haue ſlip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped or fallen, ſometimes, to confirme and corrobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate thoſe that ſtand. In a word, In this Church as in the Arke there muſt bee both <hi>manna</hi> and <hi>virga,</hi> bread for refection, and a rod for correction, <hi>oſculum</hi> and <hi>fraenum,</hi> a kiſſe for friends and a bridle for refractarie and ſtubborne perſons. And as in a Vineyard there muſt be both planting and pruning, ſo in this Church muſt there be both Doctrine &amp; Diſcipline. Doctrine, to inctruct in the points of Faith, to conſerue, nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh and augment charitie, flowing from the ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the minde, integritie of the conſcience, and from a faith voyde of diſſimulation and hypocriſie. Diſcipline, to correct and reforme vices and abuſes. Secondly, this word <hi>Church</hi> is taken for the People, the Paſtors being excluded, and ſo it is taken, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.28. Where Paſtors are exhorted to feed the Church which CHRIST hath purchaſed with his owne blood. Thirdly, it is taken for a particular Church in which both people and paſtors are comprehended, ſuch of old was the Church at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> at <hi>Corinth,</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſuch were thoſe ſeauen Churches whereof wee
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:21001:8"/> reade in the 2. and 3. Chapters of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> But now many of theſe Churches haue much fallen from that puritie wherein the Apoſtles and their Diſciples did inſtitute them, and ſome of them altogether made ſo great a defection and apoſtaſie from the faith, as therein a man explicitly reſting on their whole Doctrine cannot bee ſaued, ſuch to day is the Church at <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſuch a one hath ſhe beene theſe many ages paſt, for in her, Idolatry is maintayned, and the whole Doctrine of the benefit of CHRIST altogether corrupted, if then a man would bee ſaued, hee muſt vſe our Sauiours counſell, <hi>Revel.</hi> 18.4.<note place="margin">Reuel. 18.4.</note> 
               <hi>Goe out of Babylon my people, that yee bee not partakers of her ſinnes, and that yee receiue not of her plagues.</hi> Fourthly, this word Church is taken for the whole aſſembly of thoſe that here below vpon the earth are called Chriſtians: and this is the vniuerſall viſible Church, compoſed of diuers particular Churches, called by the Apoſtle in the 1. of <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15.<note place="margin">1. Tim. 3.15.</note> 
               <hi>The pillar and ground of truth,</hi> becauſe it is the dutie thereof to vnderprop and defend the truth againſt all thoſe that ſeeke by ſchiſmes, hereſies, and erronious Doctrines to ſuppreſſe and ouerthrow the ſame. Now this vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall Church ſubſiſteth by a perpetuall generation one ſucceeding to another, and conſiſteth of all the conuerted Iewes &amp; Gentiles that are vpon the face of this earth. It is truth that this Church was once, and before CHRIST came in the fleſh onely among the Iewes glorious, and the Gentiles then were but dogs or whelpes; In the 15. of <hi>Math.</hi> 26.<note place="margin">Math. 15.26.</note> 
               <hi>It is not good to take the childrens bread and to caſt it to whelpes.</hi> But now God perſwaded IAPHETH to dwell in SHEMS
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:21001:9"/> tent; Now God is <hi>the God of the Gentiles alſo. Rom.</hi> 3.29. Yea which is more, <hi>obſtinacie is come to Iſrael, vntill the fulneſſe of the Gentiles bee come in. Rom.</hi> 11.25. And amongſt vs God hath a more<note place="margin">The Church is more glorious among the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians then it was among the Iewes.</note> glorious Church then euer hee had amongſt the Iewes: for this cauſe ABRAHAM deſired to ſee our dayes; for this cauſe S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> PAVL called Gods old ordinances, <hi>beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerly rudiments.</hi> Gal. 4.9. and reputed of Genealogies as of fables, for this cauſe the Patriarkes <hi>without vs are not ſaid to be perfect,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11.2.</note> Heb. 11.40. And this made SIMEON for a time to deſire, <hi>that he might not ſee death.</hi> The Iewiſh Church had but ſhadowes and circumſtances, but we haue the body and the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.2.</note> The word was made fleſh; he walked among his brethren, they ſaw him, handled him, heard him, beheld his wounders and miracles,<note place="margin">Math. 27.24.35. Math. 26.6.</note> ſaw him condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, crucified, raiſed, and carried into heauen in a cloud. It was this that made EZECHIELL the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſay, our Temple ſhould bee bigger, then in the dayes of MOSES,<note place="margin">Math. 11.11.</note> that made IOHN the Baptiſt bee called the greateſt of all the Prophets, and yet the leaſt in our Church greater then he: that made S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. PAVL. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 3.</note> Call the Law, the miniſterie of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, but the Goſpell, the miniſtration of righteouſnes, the Law that which ſhould be aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but the Goſpell glorious, and that which remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth: that vnder the law the Iewes did onely ſee but thorow a vaile, but we in our Church vnder the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, behold as in a mirror the glory of the Lord with open face. O vnthankfull Gentiles! O ingratefull Chriſtians, and O moſt ingratefull England of all the Chriſtians in the world, for howſoeuer that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:21001:9"/> other Nations may pretend ſome excuſe, yet ſurely, O England, thou is vnexcuſable, eſpecially theſe 60. yeares, in which this ſunne of the glorious Goſpell hath continually without ecclipſe ſhined in thy Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizon, and ſtill doth runne his circular motion, and yet neuertheleſſe what is the darkneſſe in which wee doe not walke? Alas, I meane, what iniquitie doe we not drinke in like water? What is the vanity after the which we doe not ſeeke? And what is that grace of GOD, which wee turne not into wantonneſſe? E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially (leauing at this time all other things) this glorious Goſpell, this ſpirituall Manna, this heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly food, the plentie whereof produceth nothing but a loathing of the ſame, except it be moſt rarely cook'd in, and garniſhed with humaine conceites to ſatisfie your daintie appetites, &amp; when it is cooked to you af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this manner, which is a ſort of Preaching too much vſed in this Land, and deſerueth more diſcommenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet are yee contrary to all other creatures vnder the ſunne, that grow the fairer, the fatter, and the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter too the more choiſe diet they feede on; as for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, when trees are remoued to a more fertile ſoyle, they will ſpread further, and be more fertile then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, when cattell are put into a better paſture, they will be of a greater growth and labour better too: But it is not ſo with vs; No, for after never ſo learned a ſermon, there will be both diſliking &amp; liking of it, but this liking tendeth not to retaine the principall parts thereof in our memories and to practiſe the ſame in our liues and conuerſations. No, No, but onely a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king that the Preacher did well and that he is a good Scholler, and this is all, and, if it bee ſo, it is much
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21001:10"/> too. But O Lord I pray thee, that giueth both the will and the deed to thy people, to beſtow vpon them new hearts, to renew within their bowels a right ſpirit, that they may apprehend thy bountifulneſſe toward them, and magnifie thy Name for ſuch plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifulneſſe of thy word ſowen amongſt them, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard whereof many Nations, like a Foreſt, ſtands not put to tillage, and for ſuch light in thy glorious Goſpell, in reſpect whereof, many, yea almoſt all people are but conducted by the Moone, which I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech the O Lord neuer to extinguiſh, neuer, O Lord to let the Sunne of thy Goſpell in this Land ſet, ſo long as the Sunne and Moone endure. Fifthly the Church is taken among Chriſtians for the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and aſſembly of the Elect, and of thoſe that GOD by the way of ſanctification hath predeſtinated to bee the heyres of the Kingdome of glory: and this Church is compoſed of three ſorts of<note place="margin">The Church of the Elect com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of three ſorts of men.</note> people; firſt, of ſuch as were vpon the earth; but now are not, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their ſoules and their bodies are ſundred; their bodies till the day of judgement are committed to the graue, where they muſt returne vnto the earth out of which they were taken, but their ſoules are conjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with CHRIST in heaven, which one day ſhall bee reunited againe to their bodies, and magnifie God both in body and ſoule, and this is called <hi>The triumphant Church,</hi> becauſe the members thereof haue ouercome by the good fight of Faith, powers, princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palities, and ſpirituall wickedneſſe in this life, and now in that other life, which is much better then this, they tryumph, and haue receiued, albeit not fully, the fruits of their labour, and GOD hath giuen them
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:21001:10"/> 
               <hi>beautie for aſhes, the oyle of ioy for mourning, and the garment of gladneſſe for the ſpirit of heavineſſe.</hi> Secondly, this Church of the Elect is compoſed of men that are vpon earth preſently aliue, fighting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſinne, Sathan, the world and their owne cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt affections, making their Election ſure vnto themſelues by well doing, but or it bee long ſhall be no more, and this is the <hi>Militant Church,</hi> the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers whereof are viſible as men, but not as members of this Church, and elect men, becauſe Election is not diſcerned by the eye but charitably preſumed on by faith and good workes which are inſeparable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions; as the Sunne and light, fire and heate, water and aliquiditie: ſo that if a man want good workes, wee may boldly ſay hee hath no faith, but wee dare not affirme for all this, that hee is not a veſſell of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, becauſe Election is a thing which God hath reſerved to himſelfe, yea, it is altogether vnknowne to a man himſelfe, it runneth ſo ſecretly, vntill the time that by his internall vocation God make it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt and knowne to him, ſo that when I ſee a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane man, a perſecuter, an vnfruitfull tree; I may ſay, and that with reaſon, that ſuch a one hath no faith, and as yet is not internally called, but that God hath not elected him, and will not call him, it is a damnable preſumption, and to diue in the bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe gulfe of GODS vnrevealed will, and to fall within the compaſſe of that which our Saviour ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly diſchargeth, <hi>Math.</hi> 7.1. <hi>Iudge not that yee bee not iudged, for with what iudgement yee iudge yee ſhall be iudged.</hi> Thirdly, this Church of the Elect is compoſed of ſuch as are not, but ſhall bee, as are not
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:21001:11"/> yet borne; but are in the counſell of GOD regiſtrated and inrolled to bee borne, to fight in his warre in fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture time; and ordained to obtaine victorie.</p>
            <p>This Church of the elect<note place="margin">Foure names giuen to the Church of the elect.</note> hath many names in Scripture, eſpecially foure; Firſt, in the 1. of <hi>Pet.</hi> the 2. chapter and 9. verſe. It is called a <hi>Choſen generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and herein is diſtinguiſhed from all other Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.<note place="margin">Diſtinguiſhed from all other Churches.</note> Firſt, from the Church of the Heathen and Infidels, which is, <hi>generatio malignantium,</hi> a <hi>Wicked generation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, from the Church of the Papiſts, which is, <hi>generatio Antichriſtianorum,</hi> an <hi>Antichriſtian gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Revel. 17.</note> a <hi>great Whore arrayed in purple and ſcarlet, gilded with gold, precious ſtones, and pearles: ſitting vpon many waters, people, multitudes, Nations, tongues, and ſeaven Mountaines, which raigneth over the Kings of the earth, giving heed vnto Spirits of errour, tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching Doctrines of Devils, forbidding to marry and commanding to abſtaine from meates which God hath created to bee received with giving thankes: drunken with the blood of Saints and with the blood of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs of</hi> IESVS, I meane with the blood of many good Chriſtians as <hi>Lyons</hi> in France, called <hi>Waldenſes</hi> from IOHN WALDVS, as they call vs <hi>Calviniſts</hi> from CALVIN, whom their King to his immortall infamie and diſhonour excited by the Papacie did moſt cruelly butcher: with the blood of many good Chriſtians maſſacred vpon S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Baltholmewes</hi> day at <hi>Paris,</hi> whoſe wounds are yet freſh bleeding in the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories of men that liue and ſaw them, at <hi>Tollouſe, Orleans, Boitiers,</hi> and many more places in France: with the blood of many a hundred thouſand butche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:21001:11"/> moſt beaſtly in weſt <hi>Flanders</hi> by the Duke of <hi>Alphe,</hi> becauſe they would not <hi>receiue the marke of the Beaſt in their foreheads;</hi> what ſhall I ſay of our Martyrs vnder Q MARIES raigne, or of that Beaſts crueltie and inſatiable deſire of blood that lately heere moſt furiouſly in King IAMES his time, intended to haue blowne vp our Parliament houſe? I can ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but beleeue that that which S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> IOHN many yeares agone foretold, is fulfilled, that is,<note place="margin">Revel. 18.4.</note> that <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon even that great Citie vpon the ſeaven Mountaines is become the habitation of Devils, the hold of all foule ſpirits, a cage of every vncleane and hatefull bird.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, this Church of the elect, this Choſen ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, is diſtinguiſhed from the Church of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Heretikes and Schiſmatikes, which is, <hi>generatio reproborium,</hi> a <hi>reprobated generation,</hi> of this order are Manicheans, Arrians, Browniſts, Familiſts, and ſuch like, which eſteeme none to bee members of the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall Body of CHRIST, except thoſe, that bee of their moſt wicked and execrable opinions: Puritans I will not deale ſo rigorouſly with you, howſoever you are but tares among the wheate, and albeit you hold none to bee profeſſors of the Goſpell, but your ſeditious and Schiſmatike ſocietie, and therefore cals and termes your ſelues Profeſſors <hi>per</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that your profeſſion is nothing but lip-labour, renting in the meane ſeaſon the coate of CHRIST whereupon the barbarous Souldiers did caſt lottes, and ſpared the ſame, breaking downe the walles of Ieruſalem which * TITVS,<note place="margin">Ioſeph:</note> a heathen Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour would haue ſuffered to ſtand; drowning that Arke, which the generall Deluge would not drowne,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21001:12"/> when it drowned all the world, burning that buſhe, wherevpon the cruell raging fire had pittie and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, and In a word you endeuour by your igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and malicious Schiſmes, to demoliſh that houſe which is built vpon a rocke againſt which <hi>the gates of hell ſhall not preuaile;</hi> for when any of the faithfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of God takes paines for the home bringing of a loſt Papiſt to the true ſheepefold and Church of CHRIST, It is the firſt thing which he obiecteth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs, yee are devided amongſt your ſelues, I cannot tell whether I ſhall imbrace the opinion of your Church, or of your Puritane; and for is the conuerſion of ſinners ſtayed by your wofull generation, the kingdome of Sathan propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated, the kingdome of CHRIST diminiſhed, and Chriſtian religion expoſed both to <hi>ludibrie</hi> and <hi>oppro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brie</hi> both to mockerie and to ſhame: and yet you haue eyes and eares, but will neither ſee it nor heare it: I thinke the curſe of the Goſpell is vpon you, and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be thoſe that preferre not Ieruſalem to their chiefe joy: never may they proſper that loue not, that wiſh not peace within her ſacred walls.</p>
            <p>Fourthly and laſtly, this choſen generation is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed from the whole viſible vniuerſall Church here below, which is <hi>generatio miſcellaneorum</hi> a mixed generation, and may bee compared to a net which gathereth both fiſh and ſcorpions, to a field in which groweth both wheat and tares, to a garden in which are both weeds and flowers, becauſe in the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſall viſible Church <hi>et ſanctis Eccleſiae locis</hi> are both Chriſt and Antichriſt, Paſtors and Wolues, truth and lies; Sheepe and goates, good Chriſtians and diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:21001:12"/> hypocrites, veſſells of election and Children of wrath: and often greater ſtore of the worſt then of the beſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly againe this Church of the elect, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.32.<note place="margin">Heb. 12.32.</note> is called <hi>the Congregation of the firſt borne,</hi> whoſe names are written in heauen, becauſe the names of the elect are written in the booke of life.</p>
            <p>Thirdly <hi>Epheſ.</hi> the firſt and laſt,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.</note> it is called <hi>the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of Chriſt</hi> and by conſequence falſe, hypocriticall and prophane Chriſtians are not members thereof, becauſe ſuch are but dead members which can be no part of the liuely body of IESVS CHRIST.</p>
            <p>Fourthly <hi>Reuel.</hi> 21.9.<note place="margin">Revel. 21.9.</note> It is called the <hi>Bride</hi> and <hi>the Lambes wife,</hi> becauſe Chriſt hath married her vnto himſelfe <hi>in iudgement, in righteouſneſſe, in wiſdome, in mercy, and in compaſsion. Hoſ.</hi> 2.<note place="margin">Hoſ. 2.</note> And it is to this Church of the elect this choſen generation, this aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie, this congregation of the firſt borne, this body of Chriſt and to this Bride the Lambes wife, to which this promiſe of comfort is made.<note place="margin">Cant. 4.</note> 
               <hi>I will marrie thee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me for euer.</hi> This Church is <hi>hortus concluſus</hi> an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed peece of ground as the garden of Eden, and lieth within a hedge or fence. This Church and none other, is the ſpouſe of IESVS CHRIST, to which he hath joyned himſelfe in marriage, and which he will make vnto himſelfe a glorious Church without ſpot or wrinkle, holy and vnreproueable; and out of this Church their can be no ſaluation, in which regard ſaith St. AVSTEN, <hi>Qui Eccleſiam non habuit pro matre nunquam Deum habebit pro patre,</hi> who had not the Church to his mother ſhall neuer haue God to be his father, to which I will adde, <hi>nec Chriſtum pro capite &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:21001:13"/> marito,</hi> not Chriſt to be his head and husband; and this made the good Emperour THEODOSIVS to conclude. <hi>Malo eſſe membrum Eccleſiae quam caput Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>.</hi> I had rather be a member of the Church then head of the whole Empire. And thus much for this word Church in my text, the ſignifications and names thereof, and to which Church this promiſe is made <hi>I will marry thee vnto me for euer,</hi> to the Church of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and ſo I come to the explanation of the three ſimilitudes by which our vnion with Chriſt is moſt richly expreſſed, the firſt whereof is the ſimilitude of the roote and the grafts.</p>
            <p>Can there be a more ſtraight vnion apprehended? can there bee a more neere coniunction imagined then this betweene the ſtock and the branches, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the roote and the grafts?<note place="margin">The ſimilitude betweene the graft and the roote.</note> it is not poſſible, and yet ſuch a one is our vnion with Chriſt; In the 15. of St. <hi>Ioh.</hi> the fifth verſe,<note place="margin">Iohn 15.5.</note> 
               <hi>I am the vine yee are the branches.</hi> This is a metaphor a borrowed ſpeech from planting,<note place="margin">Three things ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruable.</note> in which yee ſhall take notice of theſe three. Firſt of the roote or ſtock, Secondly of the grafts or bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and Thirdly of the manner of ingrafting. As to the firſt, the roote or ſtock wherein this ingrafting is made, is CHRIST, called by himſelfe the true vine, by the Apoſtles the true oliue tree,<note place="margin">Rom. 11.17.</note> and by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets the roote of Ieſſe.<note place="margin">Iſa. 11.10.</note> This true vine, this true oliue and this roote of Ieſſe IESVS CHRIST, hath that great husbandman the eternall God dreſſed and prepared; in which he hath ingrafted ſo many of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dams</hi> loſt poſteritie, as he according to his purpoſe and pleaſure of his will hath decreed to make parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the kingdome of glory according to the electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:21001:13"/> of grace before the foundation of the world, and therefore in the fulneſſe of time ſent him into the world, and as it were planted him in the graue, who by and by,<note place="margin">Math. 28.</note> within the ſpace of three dayes like a liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly root ſprang vp, and reſted not till his top mounted vp to heauen, and till his branches were ſpread to the vtmoſt ends of the earth till the Goſpell was preached to the moſt remote regions vnder the Sunne, euen to the <hi>Scythians, Sauromatans, Aethiophians, Perſians</hi> and <hi>Indians,</hi> and within a ſhort ſpace after CHRISTS aſcention, which may ſeeme wonderfull, not only the Roman * Empire,<note place="margin">Tertull. adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Iudaeos. cap. <hi>7. 8.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Sed Brittanorum loca Romanis in acceſſa Euangelio Chriſti ſubdita ſunt,</hi> but euen thoſe places of Britain, ſpeaking of Scotland, which the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall ſword was neuer able to vanquiſh or ſubdue, are now vanquiſhed &amp; become ſubiect vnto the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of CHRIST, but this ſhall yet ſeeme more won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull if we ſhall but conſider thoſe that haue vanqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed both the Roman Empire and thoſe, whom the Roman Empire could not conquer, and what ſort of men they were, SOPHRONIVS Patriarch of Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem tels vs, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, our fiſhers ſaith he, our Publicanes, and that tent ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker (ſpeaking of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> PAVL) hath conſtrained all nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, all people <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to imbrace the Lawes of CHRIST crucified; and yet the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner how this was done, how this conqueſt was made, is moſt wonderfull of all: for it was done <hi>non pugnan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do,</hi> not by fighting, <hi>ſed patiendo,</hi> but by ſuffering, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering of tortures, of chaines, of impriſonings and of death it ſelfe, and the more their ſufferings was, the greater their perſecution was, the larger was their
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:21001:14"/> victories, for their blood was the ſeed of the Church and the more abundantly that it was ſowne, the Lord did reape the greater harueſt of true beleeuers to bee ingraft in him, that is their euerlaſting ſtock, and roote which neuer ſhall be conſumed by time.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Two feets of grafts.</note>The branches or grafts are twofold; externall and internall, as to the firſt, all the members of the viſible Church entred into a profeſſion of Chriſt externally, baptized with water, but not with the holy Ghoſt, may be called externall members or grafts; But this kinde of graft will ſuffer an amputation or cutting off, and will come within the preſinke of that, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.22. <hi>If thou remaine not in his bountifulneſſe thou ſhall alſo bee cut off,</hi> for they haue not the ſop of grace miniſtred vnto them from the ſtocke of life, but are as dead-trees hauing leaues without fruit, 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5. I meane good fruit; they haue fruit indeed, but it is <hi>labruſca non vua</hi> ſome ſower or hedge grape not good to eate, but no ſweet grape. Like that which grew in <hi>Baal-hamon,</hi> 8. <hi>Cant.</hi> 11. Howſoeuer it hath a faire ſhew like gawdie flowers among the corne, yet fitly it may bee compared to Sodoms apples, out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly faire, but rotten inwardly, to that which gliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters like gold but when it is touched is found to bee but copper; but moſt properly to ESAV who did lye in the bellie with IACOB, borne and brought vp in IZACKS houſe, which for the time was the Church of God &amp; marked with the ſame Sacrament of circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion too, but, becauſe he proudely diſpiſed grace, was rejected, ſo ſhall it ſtand with all thoſe that ſhall bee baptized in the true Church, and remaine not in Gods bountifulneſſe: neither ſhall it auaile them
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:21001:14"/> any thing that by an externall forme of ingrafting they haue beene joyned to the ſocietie of the viſible Church. But by the contrary it ſhall ſtand as an evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in that blacke roule and regiſter of a bad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience againſt them, and moſt juſtly ſhal it make them to be puniſhed with double ſtripes becauſe they knew their maſters will and did it not.</p>
            <p>The internall grafts are of thoſe that beſide their externall ingrafting and entering in the viſible Church by the Sacrament of Baptiſme, are alſo internally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grafted by the holy ſpirit, and the baptiſme with fire in this roote IESVS in ſuch a firme manner and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition that Chriſt is in them and they in Chriſt, they are ingrafted by Gods right hand, grounded in faith, rooted in charitie, watered by the word of Gods miniſterie, digged and manured by the diſcipline of Magiſtrates, and in euery manner of good worke brings forth a plentifull vintage of good and ſweete grapes, which are preſſed in a contrite heart, raiſed vp to a liuely and confident thankefulnes. And as wine is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly knowne by the taſt and colour ſo is this too. For its taſte is a good conſcience within, &amp; its colour is a holy conuerſation without. Theſe grafts may ſay with the Apoſtle, <hi>Now we liue, yet not we any more,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 2.20.</note> 
               <hi>but Chriſt liueth in vs.</hi> They haue in them the ſame minde that was in IESVS, and this is a faithfull wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, an vnfallible argument vnto them of their vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with Chriſt, and that they are ingrafted in him, and by the contrary, ſeeing contraries muſt bring forth contrary ſequels, thoſe that are not ruled &amp; quickned by the ſpirit of Chriſt are not ingraft in this roote, neither haue they as yet any vnion or conjunction
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:21001:15"/> with him, and ſo the Apoſtle <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.9.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.9.</note> tels vs, <hi>If any man haue not the ſpirit of Chriſt, the ſame is not his:</hi> Not aſſuredly, for thoſe that are not ruled by this ſpirit, they cannot chuſe but wander and goe aſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, walking after the fleſh, by which they cannot be abſolued from judgement, from Tophet, and adjudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnto everlaſting life, and thus much for the ſtock and grafts.</p>
            <p>And now I come to the manner of ingrafting, which is twofold,<note place="margin">A twofold in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grafting.</note> ſecret and manifeſt, ſecret in Gods eternall counſell; for before the foundation of the world was layed and long before that man was crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted God knew his owne children, and by inſerting their names in the booke of life did eternally and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all time ingraft them in this ſtocke and roote CHRIST IESVS their redeemer. Secondly it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, and done in time, but ſpiritually wrought by the holy Ghoſt who creating faith in our hearts makes vs to goe out of our ſelues, <hi>tranſire in Chriſtum</hi> tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port our ſelues into Chriſt, and ſo to relye vpon him that by his ſpirit wee are quickned, by his light wee are illuminated, and by the continuall furniture of his grace we perſeuere and increaſe in ſpirituall ſtrength and courage, and ſo liues in him that wee die in our ſelues,<note place="margin">Zach. 4.</note> and to the world. In the 4. of <hi>Zachar. As euery lampe of the golden Candleſticke hath its owne pipe thorow which theſe two Oliues which ſtand with the ruler of the whole world,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Simile.</note> 
               <hi>emptie themſelues in the gold:</hi> ſo euery member of the Church of CHRIST receiueth <hi>grace from that fulneſſe of grace</hi> which is in him thorow the ſecret conduits of the ſpirit,<note place="margin">How, and when this ingrafting is manifeſt.</note> by which hee cauſeth vs to grow and preſerueth our
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:21001:15"/> ſoules in life. Now albeit this ingrafting bee mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, and done in time, yet it is not manifeſt to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one, but onely to the graft and branch him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, for to him the ſpirit of God beareth witneſſe with his ſpirit that hee is the child of GOD, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.16.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.16.</note> But to none other, howſoeuer that his faith, fructifying in charitie, in loue, and in euery manner of good worke, may make others preſume that he is ingraft in this root by the holy Spirit, after which he is, and therefore <hi>ſavoureth the things of the Spirit, Rom.</hi> 8.5.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.5.</note> And I ſay, it is done in time, not that all Chriſtians are ingraft, that is, that there ingraf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting is made manifeſt vnto them at one certaine time, or in one ſpeciall yeare of there time: No ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but at ſuch time when it pleaſeth that great huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman the Eternall GOD, and in what age or yeare of their life vnto him it ſeemeth moſt fit: but ſure in what time ſoever it bee, it is ever in due ſeaſon and in good time, albeit it were not till the very laſt article of aſpiration, as it fell out to one of the evill doers, that was crucified with our Saviour, in the 23. of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Luke,</hi> verſe 42.<note place="margin">Luk. 23.42.</note> But ſometimes hee will ingraft and ſanctifie his Children from their mothers belly as hee did SAMVELL, IOHN the Baptiſt, and others: and ſometimes hee will let them alone till their mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle age come, and after this manner hee dealt with S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. PAVL, in the 9. of the <hi>Act.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act 9.</note> Obſcuring from him his ingrafting and Election, till his Almond tree began to flouriſh, and at ſuch a time as when hee was even breathing out Perſecutions againſt ſome of thoſe whoſe ingrafting was already made knowne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, even the Chriſtian Church in her infancie.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:21001:16"/>
            <p>O the riches of the wonderfull and incomprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble mercy of GOD declared vnto Mankinde, who hath for our ſalvation, that before were caſt-awayes and the <hi>Children of wrath,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.</note> ingrafted vs in his owne Sonne, by which hee hath put vs in a better eſtate then wee were created in: for albeit that hee made vs before in a moſt glorious manner altogether accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his owne Image, illuminated our will with Knowledge, and adorned our ſoules with Holineſſe and Iuſtice, yet hee gaue vs <hi>Naturam flexibilem,</hi> a mutable and changeable Nature, creating vs <hi>In po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtate ſtandi, ſeu poſſe cadendi,</hi> in power ſtanding or poſſibility of falling, and therefore as wee had a poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibilitie of falling, ſo wee fell indeed, and by an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtate Angell was drawne to apoſtacie. But it is farre otherwaies with vs now, by this our ingrafting in this ſtocke, and vnion with CHRIST, for as the grafts beare not the ſtocke and roote, but are borne by the ſame, and by conſequence our ſaluation dependeth not vpon our ſelues, as ADAMS did, but vpon CHRIST, which is the ſtocke in which wee are ingraft, who one day ſhall make vs <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>propter gratiam</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>qua nobis ab illo tribuetur,</hi> vnchangeable, farre aboue that eſtate, in which the Angels themſelues were cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated, by reaſon of that immutable grace which ſhall bee giuen vnto vs by him: and in this life it ſelfe, he will never ſuffer vs finally and totally to bee cut off from him by ſinne, (nothing elſe can doe it) albeit we fall in ſinne, yet God will lift vs vp againe, and raiſe vp our ſoules to a liuely confidence in our all-ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Redeemer. In the 37. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 24.<note place="margin">Pſal. 37.24.</note> verſe, <hi>Though the Iuſt man falleth, hee ſhall not be vtterly caſt downe,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:21001:16"/> for the Lord vpholdeth him with his hand.</hi> And whereas other branches may bee cut off and pulled away from their ſtocke, eyther by the violence of boyſterous and tempeſtuous windes, or by the force of men, or at leaſt conſumed by time, yet it ſhall not bee ſo with vs that are ingraft in CHRIST, becauſe wee doe not keepe him, but are kept by him, and ſo long as <hi>hee is vnchanged,</hi> ſaith <hi>Malac.</hi> 3.6.<note place="margin">Malac. 3.6.</note> 
               <hi>Wee cannot be conſumed;</hi> but the older wee be in him, the more wee flouriſh, for thoſe that are planted in <hi>the courts of the Lord flouriſh in their old age and bring forth fruit,</hi> ſaith DAVID, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 92.13.14.<note place="margin">Pſal. 92.13.14</note> But as to thoſe that are not ingraft in Chriſt, how great, how tall ſoever they bee, yea, albeit they were like the ſonnes of ANAK in ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or in height like the <hi>Oakes of Baſan,</hi> or like NA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BVCHADNEZZAR, that grew vp like a great tree ſo high that <hi>the fowles of the heaven made their neſts vnder him,</hi> yet they ſhall bee pulled away from their ſtocke, they ſhall not remaine in honour, they ſhall be brought to the graue like abominable branches. In the 40. Chapter of <hi>Eſay,</hi> the 24. verſe,<note place="margin">Eſay 40.24.</note> 
               <hi>The Princes of the earth their breath ſhall decay, they ſhall returne to their earth, and their thoughts ſhall periſh, the Iudges thereof ſhall bee made a vanitie as though they were not planted or ſowne, or as if their ſtocke tooke no roote in the earth, the Lord ſhall blow vpon them and they ſhall wither, the whirle-wind ſhall take them away as ſtubble.</hi> O pitifull glory of worldlings! which often dyeth vnto them before they die them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, at leaſt continually with themſelues, their beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie conſumeth in going from the houſe to the graue; neyther doth their pompe deſcend after them. Onely
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:21001:17"/> happie is the eſtate of thoſe that are ingrafted in CHRIST,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> 
               <hi>Neither life nor death, principalities nor powers, things preſent nor thinges to come ſhall bee able to ſeparate them from the loue of God in</hi> CHRIST IESVS their ſtocke and roote. And thus much for the firſt ſimilitude of the roote and the grafts, by which the vnion betweene CHRIST and his Church is expreſſed.</p>
            <p>As to the ſecond, it is the ſimilitude of Garments;<note place="margin">The ſecond ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude of Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> and looke what ſtraitneſſe, what neereneſſe, and how great a conjunction is betweene our bodies and our garments, which is exceeding neere, yet ſuch is the vnion betweene Chriſt and vs, and more ſtrait too, which when the Apoſtle in the 13. to the <hi>Rom.</hi> 24. verſe, deſired moſt richly to expreſſe, and moſt liuely to ſhew forth, he exhorteth vs <hi>to put on the Lord Ieſus,</hi> to put him on as a veſture and garment, to be ſo vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him, as we poſſeſſe him, and haue him in vs, and wee in him. Now thoſe that put on IESVS CHRIST are clothed with a fourefold garment;<note place="margin">Thoſe that put in Chriſt are cloathed with a fourefold gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> firſt, with a garment of CHRISTS imputed Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Secondly, with a garment of Sanctification. Thirdly, with a garment of Protection; and fourthly,<note place="margin">Three names gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto euery one of the foure garments.</note> with a garment of Glory. The firſt gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may be called a winters garment, <hi>quia tegit</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it covers vs. The ſecond may be called a ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers garment, <hi>quia ornat,</hi> becauſe it adorneth vs and maketh vs fine. The third may bee called a ſtand of armour, <hi>quia protegit,</hi> becauſe it protecteth vs. And the fourth may bee called our Wedding garment, becauſe wee muſt not put it on till our Marriage day with the Lambe. The firſt three garments may bee
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:21001:17"/> called our work a day ſuites, becauſe euery good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian muſt put them on euery day ſo long as hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth in this valley of teares here belowe. But the fourth muſt bee called our holidayes ſuite, becauſe wee muſt not put it on till the weeke of our Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage in <hi>baca,</hi> bee ended, and the day of our appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance (before GOD in <hi>Sion,</hi> in that <hi>new Ieruſalem,</hi> in which <hi>no arrow can bee ſhot</hi>) begin.</p>
            <p>I returne to the firſt garment, the garment of CHRISTS imputed Righteouſneſſe,<note place="margin">The firſt Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Chriſts righteouſneſſe.</note> and our Saviour himſelfe ſpeaketh of it, <hi>Revel.</hi> 3.18. <hi>I counſell thee to buy of mee white rayment that thou mayeſt bee cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed, and that thine filthy nakedneſſe doe not appeare.</hi> The Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> ſpeaketh of this garment too, but more plainly. GOD <hi>hath cloathed mee with the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Salvation and covered me with the robes of Righteouſneſſe.</hi> Eſay, 61.10. But what righteouſneſſe is this?<note place="margin">What righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe this is.</note> Is it not the righteouſneſſe of his Diuine na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture? No, for that is not communicable, but the glory which hee will not giue vnto another. What then? Is it not the righteouſneſſe of his Humaine na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture conſiſting in a perfect obedience of the morall Law? No, not that alone neyther; for that alone were <hi>perbrene,</hi> too ſhort, <hi>non vult tegere,</hi> it will not cover vs from the froſtie blaſts of Gods wrath, and from the fearefull winter tempeſts of his infinite Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice. What righteouſneſſe then I pray you? A righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe neuer impoſed to Man nor Angell, euen that righteouſneſſe which hee as our Mediator by ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling the ſingular law of a Redeemer hath purchaſed and acquired, to the end that hee might communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate it, and giue it freely vnto his Church for her
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:21001:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> juſtification, by which ſhee is abſolued from death, whereunto by reaſon of ſinne both originall and actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, ſhe was ſubject, and is adjudged vnto life. And this is CHRISTS imputed righteouſneſſe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with hee firſt couers thoſe that puts him on,<note place="margin">How it couers vs.</note> euen our winters garment, which is ſo perfect and ſo compleat that it covereth all our nakedneſſe from the crowne of the head to the ſole of the foote, both of body and ſoule; for in both our Mediator ſuffered; his bleſſed Head was crowned with thornes, to ſatisfie for the proud Imaginations of our ſtout braines; his ſacred hands and feete which neuer offended, were pierced with nailes of Iron, to ſatisfie for the wicked deeds which wee haue done with our hands, and runne to with our feet, and alas! daily by our ſinnes wee draw him againe to the ſame torture, <hi>and crucifie againe to our ſelues the Sonne of God, and make a mockerie of him.</hi> Heb. 6.6. Hee ſuffered the wrath of GOD in his ſoule ſo heauily, as that both heauen and earth did ſtand amazed to behold it; The Heauens did draw their curtaine, and darkneſſe was vpon the face of the earth, that they ſhould ſee their maker in ſuch paine, the Sunne for ſhame would not looke vpon the Sonne of GOD in ſuch a caſe, the vayle of the Temple rent it ſelfe in two for griefe, to ſee its Lord ſo diſhonoured, the Stones in the ſtreet did cleaue a ſunder for woe, to ſee that Stone refuſed of the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, <hi>which is the head of the corner.</hi> And finally, the Bodies of the dead roſe out of their graues, aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed to behold the Lord of life ſo troubled in ſoule, that their ſoules might in joy perpetuall peace with GOD, and be cloathed with the garments of his impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted righteouſnes.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:21001:18"/>
            <p>The ſecond garment, is a garment of Sanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.<note place="margin">The ſecond gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</note> Now wee are cloathed with this garment, when like the Elect <hi>wee put on tender mercy, kindneſſe, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe of minde, meekneſſe and long ſuffering,</hi> Col. 3.12. <hi>But ſpecially when wee put on loue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">When it is put on.</note> 1. Theſ. 5.8. Or to ſay with S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> PETER, <hi>When wee decke the hidden man of our heart with a quiet and meeke ſpirit,</hi> 1. Pet. 3.4. This is our ſummers garment which adorneth vs, and maketh vs fine, this is that pure, fine and ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning linnen, which is the righteouſneſſe of the Saints. A garment not partie coloured, as IOSEPHS was, but made of many vertues and graces of IESVS CHRIST. Theſe are the badges and cogniſances by which wee are knowne to bee his ſeruants, and the putting on thereof, is the putting on of Ieſus Chriſt. Theſe are the graces by which the Holy Ghoſt tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlateth vs out of nature, transformeth vs into the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of the Sonne of GOD, and maketh vs become one with our Redeemer.<note place="margin">When it is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vs.</note> This garment and the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer are both giuen vs at one time. The former gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of CHRISTS imputed Righteouſneſſe defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs from the fierie flames of Gods burning wrath. This garment of Sanctification, reformeth our cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted nature &amp; renueth the ſame; Theſe 2.<note place="margin">What it wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth.</note> garments both cures and couers our filthy nakednes, they turne our ſickneſſe into health, and our darkneſſe into light, for whoſoeuer putteth on IESVS CHRIST for righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes to Iuſtification, puts him likewiſe on for ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe to Sanctification. So full of grace and vertue is the Lord, that hee, not onely by the merit of his ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings pacifieth the wrath of God toward all thoſe, in whom hee is, but likewiſe by this vertue ſanctifieth
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:21001:19"/> them, and by creating a new heart within their breaſt, and a right ſpirit within their bowels, maketh them new creatures, changing them from one thing to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other both in body and ſoule,<note place="margin">Act. 26.</note> 
               <hi>from ſinne to ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, from darkneſſe to light, from death to life, and finally, from the power of Sathan to the power of God.</hi> That is, to Righteouſnes, Iuſtice, and ſoberly to walke in this life, in which, except our ſanctified carriage, (neyther is that compleat, for man heere is but onely in a part ſanctified, otherwiſe hee were more then a man, but is perfectly juſtified, or elſe were hee no more then a ſinner) all things are not onely tranſito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and vayne; But vanitie it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The <hi>3.</hi> Garment and its <hi>3.</hi> names</note>The third garment, wherewith CHRIST cloatheth his Church and thoſe that put him on, is a ſuite of compleat armour; <hi>hoc protegit,</hi> this protecteth the Chriſtian man againſt all the aſſaults of Sathan, and maketh him ſtand out againſt all the invaſions of his Spirituall enemies. Sathan enuying this vnion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene CHRIST and his Church, endeuoreth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſantly to defile the members of the ſame, to rent them a ſunder, and teare them in peeces; ſometime aſſaulting their Patience,<note place="margin">Iob. 1. Gen. 9.21. Gen. 19.33. 2. Sam. 11.4.</note> as he did IOBS; ſometime their Temperancie, as hee did to NOAH and LOT; ſometime their Continencie, as hee did to DAVID; ſometime their Humilitie, as hee did to HEZIKIAH, 2. <hi>King.</hi> 20. And made him in the pride of his heart, which of all vices is the firſt, to ſhew the treaſure of his houſe to the Ambaſſadours of BERODACH BA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LADAN King of Babell, which thereafter produced a ſtrange effect, even that not only his treaſure, but the fruites of his loynes in the reigne of IEHOIACHIN,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:21001:19"/> the people and all the ſtrongeſt men of warre were carried vnto Babell and Captiuitie, 2. <hi>King.</hi> 24. Somtime againe Satan aſſaults vs in our religion and former zeale: and it is wonderfull how almoſt he euer preuailes once againſt Gods children, howſoeuer it be true that in the end he is euermore repulſed and driuen backe againe. And in this manner he beſieged SALOMON, the ornament of the world both for knowledge and godlineſſe, prevailed againſt him, cauſed him commit Idolatry, and his Idolatrous wiues to turne his heart after other Gods, ASHTAROTH the god of the Zidonians, and MILCOM the abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the Ammonites, 1. <hi>King.</hi> 11.<note place="margin">1. King 11.</note> And laſtly, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than labours much to ſteale from Gods children their honeſt name, &amp; this is one of his moſt ſubtle aſſaults, and vſeth the tongues of his owne inſtruments to ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect his purpoſe, againſt the enemies of his kingdome, <hi>Vt qui conſcientiae ſuae luce clareſcunt falſis rumoribus ſordidentur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nazian.</note> that thoſe who through the teſtimonie and light of their innocent conſciences ſhines like the ſunne in his meridian, may be made blacke like the night, filthy as a puddle by the falſe reports of others. Good IOSEPH in the 39. chapter of <hi>Gen.</hi> was after this manner ſet vpon by one of Satans owne inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments POTIPHARS wife, for when ſhe could not arriue at the intended end of her naughtie thoughts, <hi>come and lie with me:</hi> ſhe ſtole from him his good name; this <hi>Hebrew ſeruant would haue mocked me,</hi> and ſo made him odious and filthie in his maiſters eyes, and in the ſight of his friends: and after this manner are many choſen veſſels ſet vpon by the ſouldiers of Satan ſo, as it is impoſſible for vs to keepe the whole
<pb facs="tcp:21001:20"/> peeces of our bodie together except we put on the ſuite of protection, that ſuite of compleat armor in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Epheſ.</hi> And ſtand with our loines girded about with veritie, hauing on the breſt-plate of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and the ſhooes of the preparation of the Goſpell of peace, he muſt haue in the one hand the ſhield of Faith, and in the other the ſword of the Spirit, which is the word of God; vpon our head we muſt put on the hope of Saluation for an helmet, and the ſling of Prayer muſt be in our mouthes, or rather in our hearts with ſtrong cryings &amp; inward groanings, as MOSES had it at the red Sea,<note place="margin">Exod. 14.15.</note> when PHARAOH purſued after him &amp; his people: and to theſe pieces I could yet adde one further, another paire of ſhooes; the Prophet EZEKIEL ſpeaketh of thoſe ſhooes in his 16. Chap. and they are made <hi>ex pellibus melium</hi> of Baggets skins.<note place="margin">The ſhooes of the Baggets skin why aſsigned to the Church.</note> 
               <hi>Elinie</hi> in the 38. chap. of his 8. booke <hi>Records,</hi> that <hi>melis</hi> is a beaſt not only of great innocencie, but of ſuch ſingular prudencie too, <hi>quod ſufflatae cutis diſtentione ictus hominum ac canum morſus arcere ſolet,</hi> that by the extenſion of its skin it can ſhun both the ſtrokes of men and bites of dogs, and therefore among many more tokens of Gods fauor beſtowed vpon his ſpouſe the Church, for her preſeruation, he likewiſe hath aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned vnto her the ſhooes of this beaſts skin, to teach her both innocencie and prudencie, to be innocent like a Doue, but wile like a Serpent for her protection againſt all her malignant enemies whatſoeuer. Thus muſt we walke armed continually, armed ſo long as we are in this life 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.3. as the good Souldiers of IESVS CHRIST,<note place="margin">Iob. 7.1.</note> becauſe our life, as ſaith IOB, is a warfare,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.</note> and wee muſt fight againſt Principalities,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:21001:20"/> powers, and ſpirituall wickedneſſe, and not only fight but muſt ouercome, anquiſh, and ſubdue them; and thus much for the three firſt ſuites of apparell, our workadayes ſuites, which euery good Chriſtian muſt put on every day ſo long as he is in this life heere be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe.</p>
            <p>But as to the 4. and laſt, it is a garment of Glory,<note place="margin">The <hi>4</hi> Garment, and its <hi>3.</hi> names.</note> our wedding garment and our holy dayes ſuite, but when the weeke of our warfare ſhall end, and the day of our refreſhment,<note place="margin">Act. 3.20.</note> the day of our eternall peace ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare and begin, which is our euerlaſting Sabbath,<note place="margin">Revel. 19.7.</note> our marriage day with the Lambe, after which ſhall neuer come a night, then ſhall our father cauſe this ſuite, our holy dayes ſuite, our beſt robe to be brought out and cover vs with white raiment,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.</note> then ſhall this mortall put on immortalitie, and this corruptible in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptibilitie; then ſhall we be couered with brode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red worke, and the LORD ſhall put frontlets vpon our faces, eare rings in our eares,<note place="margin">Eſay, 26.</note> bracelets about our armes, chaines about our necks,<note place="margin">Eſay, 61.10.</note> and crownes vpon our heads, yea the Lord himſelfe ſhall be vnto vs a crown of Glorie and a diadem of beautie. Thus will he deck vs as a Bride attired with Iewels,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 11.</note> as a chaſte Spouſe to be preſented to our immortall husband without ſpot or wrinkle, in whoſe face is the fulneſſe of Ioy, and at whoſe right hand are pleaſures for euermore, rivers of pleaſure in which wee ſhall bath our ſelues for all eternitie. And ſo haue you briefly the ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of the Garments.</p>
            <p>Now reſteth the ſimilitude of Marriage:<note place="margin">The ſimilitude of Marriage.</note> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed this Spirituall vnion betweene CHRIST and his Church, is very often expreſſed by Marriage in the
<pb facs="tcp:21001:21"/> old and new Teſtament. In the 45. chapter of <hi>Eſay.</hi> fifth verſe,<note place="margin">Iſay. 45.5.</note> 
               <hi>hee who made thee, is thy husband, whoſe name is the Lord of hoſtes.</hi> And in the 9. of <hi>Math.</hi> 15. <hi>Can the children of the marriage chamber mourne ſo long as the bridgroome is with them.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 9.15.</note> And yet more plainely in the 19. of the <hi>Reuel.</hi> 17.<note place="margin">Revel. 19.17.</note> 
               <hi>The marriage of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> hath come, and the bride hath made her ſelfe readie.</hi> And againe <hi>Reuel.</hi> 21.9.<note place="margin">Revel. 21.9.</note> 
               <hi>I will ſhow thee the bride; the Lambes wife.</hi> And here in my text as plainely, as liuely, and more liuely then in any other place.<note place="margin">Hoſea, 2.19.</note> 
               <hi>I will marrie thee vnto me for ever.</hi> In all which our moſt gracious God willing to expreſſe, and deſirous to ſhew foorth both that loue which hee beareth vnto vs, and that too, which he looketh for at our handes compares this moſt ſtrait vnion, this moſt neere coniunction betweene CHRIST and his Church vnto the ſacred bond of Marriage, by which two perſons the man and the woman, the husband and wife are ſo firmly conjoyned by God, that none ought to preſume to ſunder them, ſo wonderfully cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled together, that of two which they were before, now they become but one.</p>
            <p>It was already a great loue of the Lord to haue created all things for man, to haue made him Lord of them and eſtabliſhed him over the workes of his hands. DAVID in the 8. <hi>Pſal.</hi> rauiſhed with this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation breaketh out in admiration. <hi>Alas, what is man that thou are mindefull of him, and the ſonne of man that thou viſiteſt him.</hi> DAVID admired Gods liberality: toward man in the creation, but how much more ought we to admire his liberalitie, his incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible bountifulneſſe and loue toward vs in
<pb facs="tcp:21001:21"/> our redemption, wherein he not onely giueth vs his good things, But beſtowes his onely begotten ſonne <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that welbeloued ſonne in marriage on vs, and in him giueth vnto vs himſelfe too? DAVID ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mireth the contemplation of the heauens? But how much more ought we to admire the poſſeſſion of the heauens? DAVID glorifies God for the domination which he giues vs over the creatures in the earth, But how much more ought wee to glorifie God for our marriage and vnion with CHRIST, by which we ſhall reigne continually with the Angels in heauen? A marriage, I ſay, the bond whereof is the ſpirit of God, whoſe trothpligth is performed heere in the militant Church, But the nuptiall feaſt ſhal be hence in the try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant Church, where our meat ſhall be the Tree of life, our drinke the Water of life, our muſicke the ſong of the Saints, <hi>Halleluiah, halleluiah,</hi> honour, praiſe and dominion bee to him that ſitteth vpon the Throne.</p>
            <p>It is an ancient ſaying, <hi>Omnis comparatio cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>dicat vno pede,</hi> euery compariſon is lame of ſome one or other foot. But this compariſon of Marriage doth ſo fully ſet forth, ſo richly expreſſe our Spirituall marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, our conjunction with CHRIST, that if any, it goeth vpright and ſtraight in all the feete, which you ſhall quickly perceiue by taking notice of theſe ſixe things which are required in euery lawfull Marriage. Firſt, that there muſt be male and female,<note place="margin">Six Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces neceſſary in euery Marriage.</note> Man and Woman, and this may bee called conformitie of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. 2. The Marriage muſt be propounded. 3. The future Spouſe muſt be courted and wooed. 4. There muſt be mutuall gifts between the two louers. 5. There muſt bee a Matrinoniall written and ſealed. 6. There
<pb facs="tcp:21001:22"/> muſt be Procreation of children; all which, wee ſhall finde in this Spirituall marriage, but in a more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent manner. As to this word <hi>muſt</hi> ſo often repeated which importeth a neceſſitie, remember that there is a twofold neceſſitie,<note place="margin">A twofold ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity.</note> an abſolute neceſſitie, and an hypothetike; the abſolute, is when a thing is ſo neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie that it cannot be otherwayes,<note place="margin">Which Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances are ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and which hypothetikely.</note> the hyphothetike, when a thing is ſo neceſſarie that it may bee other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes but is onely profitable, decent and comely that it ſhould be ſo: So ſome of theſe circumſtances are of an abſolute neceſſitie, without which a marriage can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be, as conformitie of natures; others againe only of an hypothetike neceſſitie, and of a decent expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencie, but not abſolutely neceſſarie as giuing of mutuall gifts, writing and ſealing of a matrimoniall contract, or the like.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Church re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented by a Woman two manner of waies</note>But I returne to the purpoſe, thus being premit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and findes that in this ſpirituall Marriage, there are male and female, man and woman, for the Church is very often in Scripture repreſented by a woman, in the 4. to the <hi>Gal.</hi> 22. The Apoſtle though obſcurely, repreſents the true Church vnder the type of a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, SARAH; ABRAHAM <hi>had two ſonnes, one by a free woman, and was borne by Promiſe.</hi> But S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. IOHN, <hi>Reu.</hi> 12.1. More clearely and in a more glorious manner too; <hi>And there appeared a great wonder in heauen, a woman clothed with the Sunne, and the Moone was vnder her feete, and vpon her head had a Crowne of twelue ſtarres.</hi> Now to make vp this perfect confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie of natures, our bridgroome CHRIST IESVS, euen as the Sun, went out of the chamber of the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt heavens, from the boſom of the Father, the inviſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:21001:22"/> of the Divinitie,<note place="margin">The word is made fleſh. <hi>Gal. 4.4.</hi>
               </note> deſended downe to the earth and in the fulneſſe of time taketh our nature vpon him, becommeth man, and was like vnto man in all things ſinne onely excepted:<note place="margin">The benefit wee haue by his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note> and ſo you haue Conformitie of natures betweene CHRIST and his Church: and by it wee haue this benefit, that CHRIST of one which he was before, becomes now vnto vs three; firſt our Father in regard of our regeneration which is a new creation, a creation of new hearts within our breaſts and of cleane ſpirits within our bowels. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, our Brother in reſpect of our adoption,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.</note> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which we were but <hi>filij Irae,</hi> the children of wrath, prodigals baniſhed out of our fathers houſe, but now by our adoption wee may eate of the childrens bread, and with boldnes, cry, <hi>Abba</hi> father vnto God, the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of our Lord IESVS CHRIST, and acknowledge IESVS CHRIST his ſonne to be our elder brother. Thirdly our husband in reſpect that he hath married vs, in righteouſneſſe, in iudgement, in wiſedome, in mercy, and in compaſſion. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">The <hi>2.</hi> Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</note> it is a cuſtome that Marriage is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, and is it laudable; men ordinarily conforme to their qualitie and order, ſend their moſt truſty freinds to deale in this buſines, &amp; Kings their Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadors of their greateſt, wiſeſt, and fitteſt of their No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie to doe honour to the action,<note place="margin">This ſpirituall Marriage pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded in the moſt honourable forme for foure reſpects.</note> but neuer was there any marriage, either by King, or Emperour, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded ſo honourably as this Spirituall marriage; and that in foure reſpects. Firſt, in reſpect of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounder, God himſelfe. Secondly in regard of the parties or perſons betweene whom it was propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, which is CHRIST and his Church. Thirdly,
<pb facs="tcp:21001:23"/> in regard of the perſons to whom it was propounded, to ADAM and EVAH, the onely rulers and ſwayers of the Scepter of the whole worlds Empire, and whoſe poſteritie is now propagated in innumerable honorable Families and Princely diadems, vpon the face of the earth. Fourthly, in regard of the place where it was propounded, Paradiſe; <hi>The ſeed of the woman ſhall breake downe the head of the Serpent. Gen.</hi> 3.15. reiterated to ABRAHAM, ISAAC, and IA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>COB, to all the Patriarchs, and in all ages by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and here in my text by our HOSEA, as plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and more plainly, then by any of them; <hi>I will mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie thee vnto mee for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The <hi>3.</hi> Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. Chriſt courteth his loue.</note>Thirdly the King of Kings and Lord of Lords cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, wooeth, and in a moſt louing manner declareth his ſpirituall affection to his future ſpouſe in his let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and longs more then ſweet, penned by the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of his bleſſed ſpirit. In the fourth chap. of the <hi>Cantic.</hi> the firſt verſe. <hi>Behold thee art faire my loue, behold thou art faire, thy lips are like a thread of ſcarlet, and thy talke is comelie,</hi> and in the ſeauenth verſe, <hi>thou art all faire my loue, and there is no ſpot in thee.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine in the ninth verſe, <hi>my Siſter, my ſpouſe, thou haſt wounded mine heart, thou haſt wounded mine heart with one of thine eyes and with a chaine of thine neck;</hi> and once againe in the tenth verſe, <hi>my ſiſter, my ſpouſe, how faire is thy loue, how much better is thine loue then wine, and the ſauour of thine oyntments then all ſpices;</hi> and ſo forth thorough the whole booke of the <hi>Cantic.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chriſt for the loue of his ſpouſe fighteth a combate with his riuall.</note> In a moſt familiar manner, alluring vs and perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vs to accept of him for the loue that he beares towards vs, which was ſo great, that before his riuall,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:21001:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> Satan ſhould haue ſnatched vs out of his hand he will fight againſt him, and all his confederates, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was made fleſh,<note place="margin">Iohn 16.28.</note> 
               <hi>he went from the father and came vnto the world,</hi> he valiantly pitched a field in the wilderneſſe againſt that roaring lyon, <hi>that old Serpent,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 4.3.</note> he ouercame his chiefeſt power, he broke his wilie head, ouerthrew him in the deſart by a <hi>ſcriptum eſt.</hi> But was this all? No, he fulfilled the Law in euery point and title, ſatisfied Gods Iuſtice for vs, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he will want vs, he will giue his life for vs, and gaue it indeed, offring himſelfe in ſacrifice to the Lord of hoſts vpon the Croſſe for our ſinnes, by which he vanquiſhed hell and conquered death; and thereafter gloriouſly roſe againe, left this world, and went againe to his Father. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16.28. and ſent vnto vs the holy Ghoſt, but before he went to his fathers houſe, he told vs, that there was many dwelling places in it, and that he was going to prepare a place for vs, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14.3. and therefore exhorteth and admoniſheth vs not to be troubled, <hi>Let not your heart be troubled.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 14.1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>O what a loue is here, the hight, the breadth, the length whereof is incomprehenſible. But O what hardneſſe of heart on the contrary is vpon our part, more hardnes then if the ſtones which DEVCALION and PYRHA caſt ouer their ſhoulders after the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge had been our progenitors and the firſt authors of our race, yea then the ſtones themſelues,<note place="margin">Ouid. Metap.</note> for we reade that ſtones haue been broken in peeces at the voice of the Lord at the firſt, and ſo were the ſtones of the altar in Bethell at the voice of the Prophet, and the vale of the Temple rent it ſelfe in two, when the Lord ſuffred at <hi>Golgotha</hi> for our redemption and to make
<pb facs="tcp:21001:24"/> our marriage firme, and if at any time ſtones haue been diſobedient, vnto GODS voice, it is becauſe of mans diſobedience and infidility, in whoſe mouth it was; and in this reſpect we reade that the rocke re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to render water to MOSES at the firſt and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond ſtroke, yet rendred obedience at the third, and rendred water abundantly. But how often is this loue propounded, this marriage offred, and the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell preached vnto vs: and which is hee amongſt vs, that mollifieth his heart at the firſt, at the ſecond, yea, or at the the third ſtroake: I meane at ſo many ſermons or at a thouſand more, loueth the Lord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and repenteth him of his ſinnes and iniquities; ſhall not the Altar in Bethell, and the vale of the Temple condemne vs in the day of the Lord? that at the firſt gaue obedience; and be faithfull witneſſe of our Induration againſt vs without example, that refuſe moſt obſtinately the loue of our husband offred vnto vs euery day at our owne doores, but will not leaue our father, forſake his houſe and our owne people, will not be diuorced from our adulteries, our old ſins, that our husband the King may take pleaſure in our beautie: The Lioneſſe may teach vs wiſedome, for ſhe will not company with the Lyon after her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixtion with the Leopard till ſhe firſt waſh her ſelfe in water, vnwilling that her adultery ſhould be mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted by her ſcent. It is recorded likewiſe that the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per is ſo wiſe, that before its copulation with the fiſh <hi>Muraena,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Baſil. in his Hexamer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n Hom.</note> it firſt vomits and caſts out all the pernicious and venemous poyſon that is within it, or in its teeth; O pittifull blindneſſe of man! that by nature is more adulterous then the Lioneſſe, and goeth a
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:21001:24"/> whoring after euery ſort of vanitie, more vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous then the Viper, and is full of hatred, malice, enuie, and debate, and will neither ſee it, nor doe it away, but ſuffers ſtrange Lords to tyranniſe ouer him without repugnancie &amp; oppoſition, and ſpecially ſuch Lords as are but cowards, which if he but reſiſt, will flee from him, and yet giues way vnto him, not fearing that his diſloyalty ſhall be perceiued by his righteous maſter, head and Lord, and that his patience will in the end be turned into a ſcepter of Iron to cruſh him, and to breake him in peeces like a potters veſſell. O horrible and thrice curſed nature! why haſt thou ſo armed our carnall corps with the weapons of vnrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe to fight againſt the long ſuffring of our moſt gracious God? and ſo long to abuſe the loue of our redeemer? But let vs fight againſt nature with the weapons of righteouſneſſe, even with repentance, and humiliation, that the Lord may exalt vs, giue vs the oyle of joy for mourning, and waſh vs in that foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine opened to the houſe of Iudah: and finally let vs ſay with DAVID, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.25.<note place="margin">Pſal. 73.25.</note> 
               <hi>Whom haue we in heaven but thee, and we haue deſired none in earth with thee.</hi> And thus let vs ſay in our heart, for it is the heart which the Lord craueth, <hi>My ſonne giue me thine heart,</hi> and let vs ſay it ſpeedily, and in this life; ſpeedily, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe time ſwiftly paſſeth, <hi>Et dies noſtri ſunt vel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res curſore,</hi> our dayes are ſwifter then a poſt, ſaith <hi>Iob.</hi> 7.6. and we cannot tell how quickly the race thereof ſhall be run out, and then it will be out of time: It muſt be then in this life, which is <hi>tempus acceptum,</hi> the <hi>accepted time, the day of ſaluation.</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.2. becauſe this life is the time in which our election muſt be
<pb facs="tcp:21001:25"/> made ſure, and ſealed vp to our ſpirits by the infallible teſtimonie of the good ſpirit of God, this life is the time wherein euery man muſt worke out his ſaluation with a filiall feare and trembling: this life is the time wherein we muſt be admitted into the kingdome of grace, if euer we looke to be admitted into the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of glory: In this life we muſt be matriculated into the myſticall body of the Church by obeying the injunctions and will of God, and requiring our ſuiters loue with true affection, if euer we wil look to ſit at the bridegroomes table, and enter with oile in our lampes into his chamber into the kingdome of heauen: and in a word we muſt haue heauen in inchoation in this life, if we will haue it in perfection after this life.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The <hi>4.</hi> Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</note>Fourthly, as there are mutuall gifts betweene two perſons to be joyned in the honourable and vndefiled bed of marriage, ſo is there betweene Chriſt and his Church.<note place="margin">Chriſts guifts to the Church two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold.</note> CHRIST giueth his firſt, which are twofold, for his Church, and to his Church: for his Church, he ſendeth to his father the gifts of his righteouſneſſe and meretorious ſatisfaction for her juſtification. To his Church he ſendeth the gifts of his mercy &amp; compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, of Election, Predeſtination, juſtification, Voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Sanctification and hope of Glorification. The Church is not ingratefull,<note place="margin">The Churches guifts twofold.</note> but hath her two-fold gifts too. Contrition, and Thankeſgiuing; the firſt, is a compoſition: the ſecond a ſimple without ingredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents. The ingredients whereof Contrition is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed,<note place="margin">The ingredients thereof Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is compoſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> two.</note> are our ſinnes and a godly ſorrow for the ſame; for the child of God, a member of this Church, and everie member of the ſame, takes all their ſinnes, at leaſt ſo many of them as they know, and in a ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb facs="tcp:21001:25"/> heart as in a morter beateth them, ſo as they are borne downe in ſome meaſure, yea in a great meaſure, &amp; never riſeth vp ſo high therafter: and therof is Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition compoſed &amp; made: which is ſent vp by deuout prayer, and innumerable ſighes which cannot be vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, whereof the Lord moſt willingly accepteth, for the <hi>Sacrifices of the Lord are a contrite ſpirit,</hi> ſaith DA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VID, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.17. <hi>A contrite and a broken heart, O God, thou wilt not deſpiſe.</hi> The other gift, Thankeſgiuing,<note place="margin">Thankeſgiuing the greateſt gift which wee can giue vnto God,</note> is a ſimple and hath none ingredients, But is a volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie, a willing retribution of one good thing for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, a ſweet and a godly reioycing in the vndeſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued mercies of God, which is one of the greateſt gifts which we can, or are able to offer vnto God, in which regard the Apoſtle exhorts vs alwaies, in all things to giue thankes, 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.18.<note place="margin">Prayer and Thankeſgiuing paralelled.</note> Prayer &amp; Thankſgiuing are two notable parts of diuine worſhip, but of the two, Thankeſgiuing is the moſt heavenly and Angelike: for in Prayer we reſpect our ſelues and haue regard vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuch things as wee deſire to haue; But by Thankeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing we retribute vnto God what is competent vnto him, &amp; only regards his Divine eſſence. Prayer againe properly pertaines to vs whileſt we are in <hi>baca,</hi> this va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley of teares, <hi>Et eſt egentium ac miſerorum,</hi> and belongs to wanting and miſerable people: But Thankeſgiuing ſhall pertaine to vs when all teares ſhal be wiped from our eyes, <hi>Et eſt angelorum ac glorificatorum,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs vnto vs when we ſhall raigne like Angels and be joyned to the fellowſhip and ſocietie of the glorified Church, the ſpirits of perfect and bleſſed men, that ſings continually, <hi>Praiſe bee vnto God,</hi> and <hi>Glory to the Lambe that ſitteth vpon the throne for evermore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fiftly, there is a contract,<note place="margin">The <hi>5.</hi> Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</note> a matrimoniall written and
<pb facs="tcp:21001:26"/> ſealed, in which it is contracted, that God ſhall be out God, and we ſhall bee his people, that whoſoeuer is wearie and <hi>laden,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 11.</note> that in comming to our redeemer he ſhall be eaſed, and refreſhed, which is, he ſhall be pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from all his ſinnes in the blood of his Sauiour, for in the 3. of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Iohn</hi> 36. <hi>The blood of Chriſt purgeth vs from all ſinne.</hi> This contract is written by the Apoſtles, the penmen of the holy Ghoſt, that led them in all truth and veritie, ſealed with the blood of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, and ratified by the blood of many a Martyr ſince, both vnder the firſt and the ſecond beaſt, vnder the cruell Emperours, and raging antichriſtian Popes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The <hi>6.</hi> Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</note>Sixtly, as the procreation of children is neceſſarie in Earthly marriage, ſo is it in this ſpirituall marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age. In earthly marriage this was the bleſſing of God in the beginning,<note place="margin">Gen. 2.15.</note> 
               <hi>Increaſe and multiply. Gen.</hi> 2.15. And without this, there is often but little content in mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, when the Lord had promiſed to ABRAHAM twiſe the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> to be his buckler and excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding great reward, all was nothing, there could be no true contentment; becauſe, ſaid he, I goe childleſſe. But when IZACK was promiſed, when the Lord told him that SARAH ſhould beare him a ſonne, then A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BRAHAM fell vpon his face and laughed. <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.17. and when he was borne SARA confeſſed that the Lord had made her to rejoyce.<note place="margin">Gen. 21.6.</note> * RACHELL was more impatient, for in the 30. of <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. ſhe would either haue children or die, but when IOSEPH was borne ſhe was content that God had taken away her rebuke. And in the 1. of <hi>Samuel,</hi> HANAH one of the wiues of ELCANAH did weepe becauſe ſhe was barren, but when <hi>Samuel</hi> was borne ſhe rejoyced, and brake out in this glorious triumph; <hi>mine heart reioyceth in the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:21001:26"/> Lord, mine horne is exalted in the Lord, mine mouth is enlarged over mine Enemies.</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.1. Iuſt ſo there could be no peace if in this ſpirituall marriage the ſpouſe ſhould be barren; and howſoeuer that in ſome earthly marriages for other reſpects there may be peace with barrenneſſe, and loue too. Yet in this ſpirituall marriage the procreation of children is of an abſolute neceſſitie, and muſt not ceaſe, nor leaue off till the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummation of the world, neither ſhall the world ſubſiſt any longer, then till the Church be barren, for then, the whole and full number of thoſe whoſe names are written in the booke of life are brought out, and come into the world, and then ſhall the world end, and not till then.<note place="margin">Who are our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and mother in this ſpirituall Marriage.</note> Now our Parents in this ſpirituall marriage is Chriſt, and Ieruſalem, the Church militating here below, &amp; the procreation is made at the preaching of the Goſpell by the operation of the holy Spirit: and after this manner, at one Sermon made by S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. PETER, <hi>Act.</hi> 2. there was 3. Thouſand children procreated vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt, three thouſand ſoules turned to the faith of IESVS, and whereſoever this Goſpell is preached, or ſhall be preached, the Church will never be barren, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Lord addeth daily vnto <hi>his Church ſuch as ſhould bee ſaved:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 2.</note> and in whatſoever place of the world there is any of thoſe, whoſe names are written in the booke of life, for their cauſe &amp; converſion the Goſpell ſhall be preached in that ſame place, &amp; that piece that is called their hearts ſhall be disforeſted, put to tillage and turned into a fertile field or a fruitfull garden, and if there were but one elected Familie in a whole Citie, the Goſpell will come to that City for that one families vocation,<note place="margin">Luk. 19.1.</note> as it did * to Ierico for the vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>of Zacheus and his familie:</hi> and whereſoever this
<pb facs="tcp:21001:27"/> Goſpell is not preached, it is a ſure argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that there is none of Gods choſen childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in that place, for where there is a harueſt, God will ſend reapers, and labourers where he will plant a vineyard, and when there is but little preaching in a Pariſh or a Citie, it is a token that God hath no great harueſt in that place, and where the lampe of the Goſpell hath been burning once in a glorious manner, and now is extinguiſhed, the candleſtick remoued, and falſe lights ſet vp in the place thereof, as in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> it is euident that the Lords harueſt is done in that Citie, place or Pariſh, becauſe the Lord will neuer call home the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers otherwiſe in the noone time of the day; nor remoue his Miniſtrie from his owne peoples con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion, conſolation, and farther corroboration, in which regard the Miniſters of Gods word in ſome reſpect are the parents of all Chriſtians, that is both their father and their mother, Iuſtified by S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 4.15.</note> 
               <hi>Paul.</hi> In Chriſt Ieſus, faith he, <hi>I haue begotten you, through the Goſpell.</hi> And here it is cleere that they are the fathers of Chriſtians, and<note place="margin">Gal. 4.19.</note> he makes it plaine that they are the mothers of all Chriſtians too. <hi>My little children of whom I trauell againe in birth till Chriſt bee formed in you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Gods Miniſters the Parents of Chriſtians.</note>And this ſhould teach all Chriſtians reuerently to ſpeake of their Miniſters, to honor them &amp; maintaine their reputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as their begetters to be the heirs of the kingdom of heauen; &amp; to ſupply them in their neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties as their ſpirituall parents: But the omiſſion of this dutie toward the miniſterie, argues that Chriſt is not yet formed in them, which is the forming of them to Chriſts Image and ſimilitude by caſting off the old man, which cannot be done without ſorrow and paine
<pb facs="tcp:21001:27"/> like a woman in her labour, whereof as yet they haue neuer ſo much as once felt the leaſt ſmarting: But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt be formed in them, they will be ſenſible of it: for if a woman cannot be deliuered of her child which ſhe hath carried but nine moneths in her wombe without dolour and griefe? ſhall we thinke to be deliuered of ſinne, which is a man, an old man, and a man which we haue carried about within our breaſts ever ſince the day of our natiuitie without ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall dolour and paine. No? it is not poſſible, for in a ſinners conuerſion and forming of him according to the Image of the ſonne of God, there muſt bee the broken heart, the contrite Spirit, the mourning weed, the pale countenance, the melting eye, and the voice of lamentation: and therefore Repentance receiues theſe three names in Scripture, Regeneration,<note place="margin">Three names gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</note> Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, and Mortification, and as there can be no cutting of the fleſh, no death, no birth without paine, ſo in this ſpirituall birth,<note place="margin">Wherein conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the paine in the ſpirituall birth.</note> in this forming of ſinners to the Image and ſimilitude of Chriſt there is paine; paine for their owne ſins paſt, paine for the iniquities of the wicked, becauſe they will not keepe Gods law, paine for all the abominations in the Land and place wherein they liue, paine for to ſee the Church of God ſo oppreſſed in many places of the world, and finally, paine for their abſence from their country the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen. Thoſe that are after this manner in labour and paine are the children of Chriſt begotten in this ſpirituall marriage, not by the will of fleſh and blood, but by the will of God. And thus much for the three ſimilitudes by which our vnion with Chriſt is expreſſed.</p>
            <p>And now I come to the two qualities of this Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age,<note place="margin">The two quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of this marriage.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:21001:28"/> the certaintie and the perpetuitie, but becauſe the time is ſpent, &amp; I feare that I haue ſtayed you too long I will diſpatch them in a word. The certaintie then of this marriage, as I told you, is implyed in the gemina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and doubling of this Promiſe, <hi>I will marrie thee to me, yea I will marrie thee.</hi> And this is no tautologie or vaine repetition, but an infallable truth iuſtified by <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 41.32.</note> that tels vs, that <hi>Pharaohs</hi> dreame was doubled, becauſe the thing is eſtabliſhed by God. It is truth that Gods promiſes are as ſufficient when they are but once made as when they are reiterated, as firme when they are ſpoken, as being ſworne &amp; confirmed with an oath: yet for to ſupply our weakenes and defects, our moſt gracious God is not only willing to promiſe, but often to double &amp; redouble his promiſes, as he did to <hi>Abraham</hi> in the booke of <hi>Geneſis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 12.2. Gen. 13.14.17. Gen. 15.18. Gen. 18.8.</note> when hee promiſed vnto him the land <hi>Canaan,</hi> not once, twiſe, or thrice, but fiue times. And here in my text, not once or twiſe <hi>I will marrie, I will marrie thee,</hi> but the third time; <hi>yea I will euen marrie thee.</hi> Not only content to ſpeake, but to ſweare, as in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 12.11. <hi>The Lord hath ſworne vnto David, and he will not ſhrinke from it, that of the fruit of thy body will I ſet vpon thy throne.</hi> The Apoſtle<note place="margin">Heb. 6.</note> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the reaſon, and tels vs wherefore this is done, <hi>that thereby</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>he might declare to the heires of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe the ſtabilitie of his counſell.</hi> And looke how ſtable and how ſure that our Election bee, the certaintie of this Marriage is as ſure, and what arguments and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons may be, or can be brought to proue the certaintie of the one, the ſame will ſerue to proue the certainty of the other, but at this time I will neither weary you, nor loſe my ſelfe in ſuch a wilderneſſe of diſcourſe: for none can be members of this Marriage but the Elect.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:21001:28"/>
            <p>The laſt qualitie of this Marriage is perpetuitie, for euer. This ſpeech <hi>for euer</hi> is taken 3. manner of wayes<note place="margin">This ſpeech for euer taken three manner of waies</note> in Scripture; firſt, for the time of a mans life only, and ſo it is taken <hi>Pſal.</hi> 121.8. <hi>The Lord ſhall preſerue thy go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out and thy comming in from henceforth and for euer;</hi> that is, all the dayes of thy life, &amp; that notwithſtanding of the ſpeculatiue interpretations of many that hath commented this place, that can draw out <hi>quidlibet ex quolibet,</hi> gold out of droſſe; or rather turne gold with their metaphyſicke contemplations into droſſe, whoſe opinions I cannot now ſtay to refute. Secondly, in the old Teſtament it is extended, ſomtimes to the Meſſias his comming in the fleſh, ſo is it taken <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. Where the Sacrament of Circumciſion is called a Couenant for euer,<note place="margin">Circumciſion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhed.</note> &amp; yet you know it was aboliſhed at the inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of Baptiſme, and S. <hi>Paul</hi> in diriſion cals it Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion, and in 2. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. a Bondage. Likewiſe in the 12. Chap. of <hi>Exodus,</hi> the Paſſouer is called an Ordinance of the Lord to be kept holy for ever.<note place="margin">The Paſſouer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brogated.</note> Neuertheleſſe it was abrogated at the inſtitution of the ſacrament of the Lords ſupper; Thirdly, it is taken not only for the whole time of the worlds induring, but likewiſe for that Eternity which ſhall bee after the conſummation of the world, and ſo it is taken <hi>Revel.</hi> 11.15. where it is ſaid, That Chriſt ſhall raigne for ever; and here in my text, <hi>I will marrie thee vnto mee for euer.</hi> No time here, no time hence, ſhall repudiate, ſunder, and diuorce vs, but as I haue loued my Church before all time, ſo will I continue my affection towards my welbeloued after all time, and when there ſhall be no more time.</p>
            <p>But ſeeing time is ſpent let vs winde vp this clew, let vs ſee what wee ſhall render vnto the Lord for ſo great fauor beſtowed vpon vs, for ſo great loue ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:21001:29"/> toward Mankinde, aboue the Angels, in marrying himſelfe vnto vs; making vs ſure of this marriage, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luring vs to conſtancie by louing ſpeeches, and by great promiſes perſwading vs, yea drawing vs to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace it: and ſuffring the Angels to lie ſtill vnder the heauie burden of his wrath, in the moſt wofull and moſt miſerable eſtate of Apoſtacie? What ſay I, ſhall we render vnto the Lord for ſo incomprehenſible a benefit, and ſuch an infinite weight of loue? ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand rivers of oile, &amp; all the beaſts on thouſand moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, yea in all the forreſt of Libanon are nothing to the Lord. What then? heare the Apoſtle? Loue the Lord becauſe he hath loued vs firſt, let our hearts melt with kindneſſe toward him, then ſhall it be vnto vs a faithfull witnes that we are a part of his myſticall body, a part of the Church of the elect his ſpouſe; and that the Lord loueth vs: for this loue is the firſt effect of our faith, the moſt expreſſe trace of Gods Image, and the moſt liuely marke of his children; it is the ſoule of other vertues, the rule of our actions, and the ſummarie of the Law, it is the vpholder of Martyrs, the ladder of heaven &amp; the peace of conſcience: yea, I dare ſay, that it is a taſt, a beginning here of that infinit loue which hence we ſhall carrie toward Chriſt our husband when we ſhall be preſented vnto him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſpot or wrinkle, a moſt chaſte ſpouſe, vnited, and perfectly haue this promiſe of marriage conſumma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and fulfilled. To this our husband and redeemer, with the Father, and the holy Spirit, three perſons, and one Deitie, be all honour, praiſe, and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, for now and euermore. AMEN.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:21001:29"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
